<data>

<event isBand="true" isDuration="true" start='0' end='450' earliestEnd='445' title="Cuticle (cutin)" link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plant_cuticle" image="../images/impevents/IEcuticle.jpg"> Image: Waxy cuticle &lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;p&gt; 
&lt;a href='https://camtools.cam.ac.uk/site.html?siteid=7b21d622-f8a2-43ed-003c-6e56e8f7e9cc#tool4' target="_blank" &gt; Part 1a: The Origin and Evolution of Plants: Lecture 2 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
The ability to withstand desiccation has required the novel evolution of morphological and physiological features.  Land plants cover themselves with a water-proof membrane or cuticle. This cuticle has a wax called cutin, a hydrophobic polymer.  Plants do not get waterlogged in the rain, so cuticles are effective barriers.  Cuticles are highly resistant to chemical and biological decay, and they present a barrier to fungal invasion, but they are impermeable to gases.
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
Find out more:
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;p&gt; 
&lt;a href='http://arjournals.annualreviews.org/doi/full/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.29.1.263 target="_blank" &gt; Bateman et al (1998) Early evolution of land plants. Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics, 29:263-292 &lt;/a&gt;
</event>

<event isBand="true" isDuration="true" end='430' start='0' earliestEnd='415' title="Phloem/Xylem" link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xylem" image="../images/impevents/IE1aphloemxylem.jpg"> Image: SEMs of tracheids 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;p&gt; 
&lt;a href='https://camtools.cam.ac.uk/site.html?siteid=7b21d622-f8a2-43ed-003c-6e56e8f7e9cc#tool4' target="_blank" &gt;Part 1a: The Origin and Evolution of Plants: Lecture 2 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
Plants grew in size due to a specialised transport system for water, nutrients and photosynthates, known as the vascular system.   This involved the evolution of long columns of water conducting cells joined into continuous tubes.  This is the xylem. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt; As land plants developed in complexity, a transport mechanism for photosynthates also developed to deliver sucrose around the plant. This is the phloem. Phloem cells remain alive to function, so lignin is absent.  Phloem transports massive quantities of photosynthate below ground to the roots which act as foragers and anchorage. 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
Find out more:
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href='http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/49/suppl_1/255/ target="_blank" &gt; Edwards et al (1998) Stomata in early land plants. J Exp Bot 49:255-278 &lt;/a&gt;
</event>

<event isBand="true" isDuration="true" end='430' start='0' earliestEnd='415' title="Stomata" link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stomata" image="../images/impevents/IE1astomata.jpg"> Image: SEM of leaf surface with a stoma showing the two controllable guard cells around the pore 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;p&gt; 
&lt;a href='https://camtools.cam.ac.uk/site.html?siteid=7b21d622-f8a2-43ed-003c-6e56e8f7e9cc#tool4' target="_blank" &gt;Part 1a: The Origin and Evolution of Plants: Lecture 2 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
The solution to gas impermeability is to pierce controllable holes in the cuticle. These stomata have a pair of cells with flexible walls which can create a hole as required.  They limit water loss while providing a channel for gaseous diffusion in and out. Stomata evolved with the ascent from the surface of the earth into the turbulent, dehydrating air. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt; Inside plants, ramifying open pathways developed providing a massive area of damp cell surface for gaseous diffusion.  This aerenchyma tissue in plants is equivalent to alveoli in mammalian lungs, and both are adaptations to the terrestrial environment. 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
Find out more:
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href='http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/49/suppl_1/255/ target="_blank" &gt; Edwards et al (1998) Stomata in early land plants. J Exp Bot 49:255-278 &lt;/a&gt;
</event>

<event isBand="true" isDuration="true" end='425' start='0' earliestEnd='400' title="Lignin" link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lignin" image="../images/impevents/IE1alignin.jpg"> Image: SEM of xylem vessels, showing rings of lignin 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;p&gt; 
&lt;a href='https://camtools.cam.ac.uk/site.html?siteid=7b21d622-f8a2-43ed-003c-6e56e8f7e9cc#tool4' target="_blank" &gt;Part 1a: The Origin and Evolution of Plants: Lecture 2 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
The cellulose of xylem walls is strengthened with a polymer of phenylpropanoid units called lignin. Lignin is both water-resistant and antibiotic.  Xylem cells cannot survive coating with lignin so programmed cell death apoptosis) takes place during development.  &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt; Xylem provides water conduction, structural support and defence. Lignin gives compression resistance - you cannot push a cane into a disk - but gives flexibility for bending and stretching. Lignin thus allows the photosynthetic areas to be thrust upwards towards the light. Lignin is a remarkable polymer which first evolved in the stoneworts as an anti fungus defence! 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
Find out more:
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href='http://arjournals.annualreviews.org/doi/full/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.29.1.263 target="_blank" &gt; Bateman et al (1998) Early evolution of land plants. Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics, 29:263-292 &lt;/a&gt;
</event>

<event isBand="true" isDuration="true" end='400' start='0' earliestEnd='385' title="Roots" link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Root" image="../images/impevents/IE1aroots.jpg"> Image: Plant roots 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;p&gt; 
&lt;a href='https://camtools.cam.ac.uk/site.html?siteid=7b21d622-f8a2-43ed-003c-6e56e8f7e9cc#tool4' target="_blank" &gt; Part 1a: The Origin and Evolution of Plants: Lecture 2 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
As plants grew skywards, they moved into habitats deficient in water and nutrients.  These must come from the soil by absorption through specialised roots.  But roots are in the dark so themselves need a supply of photosynthate. Early land plants had no roots.  These evolved later with the clubmosses. Roots have two functions:  i. stabilisation, and ii. nutrient and water uptake. 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
Find out more:
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href='http://arjournals.annualreviews.org/doi/full/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.29.1.263 target="_blank" &gt; Bateman et al (1998) Early evolution of land plants. Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics, 29:263-292 &lt;/a&gt;
</event>

<event isBand="true" isDuration="true" start='0' end='450' earliestEnd='445' title="Fungal Interactions" link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mycorrhiza" image="../images/impevents/IE1afungal.jpg" > 
Image: Root-fungus association 
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 
&lt;a href='https://camtools.cam.ac.uk/site.html?siteid=7b21d622-f8a2-43ed-003c-6e56e8f7e9cc#tool4' target="_blank" &gt;
Part 1a: The Origin and Evolution of Plants: Lecture 2 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;br/&gt; 
Fungi live in the soil and obtain all or part of their essential growth requirements from root exudates and dead root cells. The fungi in turn absorb nutrients from the soil and release them to the cells of the host. A mutualistic symbiosis occurs which is known as a mycorrhiza. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt; Recently, the antiquity of VAM has been demonstrated.  In the fossil vascular plant Aglaophyton from the Lower Devonian (more than 400 million years ago) there are arbuscules in the cortex, just as in modern plants. The first land plants, then, were probably mycorrhizal and relied on fungi for their phosphate.  So colonisation of land by plants was unlikely to have occurred except through the interaction with fungi. 
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
Find out more:
&lt;br/&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href='http://arjournals.annualreviews.org/doi/full/10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.29.1.263 target="_blank" &gt; Bateman et al (1998) Early evolution of land plants. Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics, 29:263-292 &lt;/a&gt;
</event>


</data>
